<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Habits on Gustavo Santana</title>
    <link>https://gustats.com/tags/habits/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Habits on Gustavo Santana</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://gustats.com/tags/habits/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Habits</title>
      <link>https://gustats.com/posts/books/atomic_habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 14:52:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gustats.com/posts/books/atomic_habits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Atomic Habits by &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A habit is a routine or behavior that is performed regularly - and in many&#xA;cases, automatically&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Changes that seem small and unimportant at first, will compound into remarkable&#xA;results if you&amp;rsquo;re willing to stick with them for years.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-surprising-power-of-atomic-habits&#34;&gt;The surprising power of atomic habits&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Habits are the compound interest of self improvement. Every day counts for a&#xA;lot in the long run&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Getting 1% better each day will make you ~38% better after one year.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Getting 1% worse each day, will decrease your performance to ~0% after one year.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Habits are a double-edged sword. They can work for you or against you.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Small changes appear to make no difference until you cross a critical&#xA;threshold. The most powerful outcomes of any compounding process are delayed.&#xA;Patience is key. Example of critical threshold:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;raising the temperature 1 degree at a time unti an ice cube starts melting&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tectonic plates that have been coliding from years until one day they&#xA;produce an earthquake.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Atomic habits are little habits that are part of a larger system. They build&#xA;the blocks of remarkable results.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For better results, forget about setting goals and focus on building a system&#xA;instead.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your&#xA;sytems.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-your-habits-shape-your-identity&#34;&gt;How your habits shape your identity.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The 3 levels of change:&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome&lt;/strong&gt; eg. stop procrastinating&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt; eg. define a schedule&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity&lt;/strong&gt; eg. &amp;ldquo;I am a productive person&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The most effective way is to focus not on what you want to achieve, but on&#xA;who you wish to become. Eg. instead of saying &amp;ldquo;No thanks, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to quit&#xA;smoking&amp;rdquo;, say &amp;ldquo;No thanks, I&amp;rsquo;m not a smoker&amp;rdquo;; focus on the identity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Your identity emerges out of your habits, every action is a vote for the type&#xA;of person you wish to become. Everytime you perform a good or bad habit, it&amp;rsquo;s a&#xA;vote that reinforces your identity. If you procrastinate, you are voting for&#xA;&amp;ldquo;I am a procrastinator&amp;rdquo;, if you do your tasks it is a vote for &amp;ldquo;I am productive&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;In the end, the goal is that the majority of votes define you as the person that&#xA;you want to be.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Becoming the best version of yourself requires to continiously edit your&#xA;beliefs, and to upgrade and expand your identity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The real reason many habits matter is not because they can get you better&#xA;results (although the can do that), but because they can change your beliefs&#xA;about yourself. Going from Identity to Outcome instead of the other way around,&#xA;is the best way of creating good habits and removing bad ones.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-build-better-habits-in-4-simple-steps&#34;&gt;How to build better habits in 4 simple steps&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
